<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The praise of a pretty lasse: or, The young mans dissimulation: else hee would not disgrace a maiden in such fashion, to the tune of, Bank's game.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00568</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20183</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.7[308]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99884374</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99884374</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183079</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00568)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183079)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A5:1[163])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The praise of a pretty lasse: or, The young mans dissimulation: else hee would not disgrace a maiden in such fashion, to the tune of, Bank's game.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By M.P. for F. Grove, neere the Sarazens Head with-out New-gate.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1638?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Verse: "Young men and maidens, to you Ile declare ..."</note>
                  <note>In two parts, separated for mounting; woodcuts at head of each part.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb n="308" facs="tcp:183079:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <head>The Praiſe of a pretty Laſſe: <hi>OR,</hi>
               <l>The Young mans diſsimulation:</l>
               <l>Elſe hee would not diſgrace</l>
               <l>A Maiden in ſuch faſhion,</l>
            </head>
            <opener>To the tune of, <hi>Bank's Game.</hi>
            </opener>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>YOung men and Maidens, to you Ile declare,</l>
                  <l>I loue my Loue, and ſhe loueth me:</l>
                  <l>Yet toke Goddeſſe will I her compare,</l>
                  <l>And yet ſhe is pretty indifferent faire;</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>With ô my Love ô, there is none doth know</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>how I doe love thee.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She is not blacke, nor yet is ſhe browne,</l>
                  <l>I loue my Loue, and ſhe loueth me:</l>
                  <l>But to her Portion, ſhe hath thirty pound,</l>
                  <l>Beſides all this, ſhe hath an old blacke Gowne:</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my love ô, there's none &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She is not great, nor yet very ſmall,</l>
                  <l>I loue my Loue, and ſhe loueth me:</l>
                  <l>She's a yard and a halfe in the waſte, that is all,</l>
                  <l>Her fleſh will preſerue her hard bones from a fall:</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my Love ô, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her Haire is as blacke as is any Crow,</l>
                  <l>I loue my Loue, and ſhe loueth me:</l>
                  <l>Her good conditions there's no man doth know,</l>
                  <l>For ſhe neuer came where as any did grow:</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my Love ô, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She hath a Noſe in the middſt of her face,</l>
                  <l>I loue my Loue, and ſhe loueth me:</l>
                  <l>And that ſtandeth brauely vnto her owne grace,</l>
                  <l>I <unclear>dare</unclear> ſay a better ne're ſtood in that place:</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my Loue ô, there is none doth know</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>how I doe love thee.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her Chéekes are fat, and faire for to ſee,</l>
                  <l>I loue my Loue, and ſhe loueth me:</l>
                  <l>They with her Eyes wondrous well doe agrée,</l>
                  <l>She is a braue bonny Laſſe louely and frée:</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my Love ô, there's none doth know</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>how I doe love thee.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She hath ſoft Lips, and ſound ones they are,</l>
                  <l>I loue my Loue, and ſhe loueth me:</l>
                  <l>You may kiſſe your fill, and neede not to ſpare,</l>
                  <l>For there is no danger of wearing thrid-bare:</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my Love ô, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She hath a Chin, and a chopping one,</l>
                  <l>I loue my Loue, and ſhe loueth me:</l>
                  <l>She might ſpare half on't for her that hath none;</l>
                  <l>But now her long Chin, I will let that alone:</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my Love ô, there's none &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her Necke doth ſhine like a Chimney ſtocke,</l>
                  <l>I loue my Loue, and ſhe loueth me:</l>
                  <l>When ſhe her Casket of Pleaſures vnlocke,</l>
                  <l>I am caught as the Miller did catch his Mare <hi>Brock:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my Love ô, &amp;c</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her downy Breaſts are ſwingers indéed,</l>
                  <l>I loue my Loue, and ſhe loueth me:</l>
                  <l>She may carry them on her ſhoulders for need,</l>
                  <l>O ſhe's a braue Laſſe we want more of her bréed;</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>With ô my Love ô, there is none doth know</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>how I doe love thee.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="309" facs="tcp:183079:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
               <head>The ſecond Part,</head>
               <opener>To the ſame tune.</opener>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>HEr ſhoulders I think, they are a whole yard ſquare,</l>
                  <l>I love my Lov<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; Lov<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e loveth me:</l>
                  <l>Sh<gap reason="illegible" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>l brave out her labour <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou need not to fear,</l>
                  <l>Give me ſuch a Laſſe that is able to beare.</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my love O, there is none doth know</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How I doe love thee.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like wiſe ſhe hath good luſty ſtrong Armes,</l>
                  <l>I love my love and ſhee loveth me:</l>
                  <l>They are able to attend her body from harms,</l>
                  <l>To ſet forth her praiſes it me much concernes,</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my love O, there is none &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hand like <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhoulder of Mutton appesres,</l>
                  <l>I love my Love and ſhée <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>veth me:</l>
                  <l>But I would not have he<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap> about mine ears,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> my love ther is no Laſſe that dares,</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my love O, there is none &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She hath ſtrong poſt legs her body to beare,</l>
                  <l>I love my Love, and ſhée loveth me:</l>
                  <l>She need dread no failing, that ſhe doth not feare</l>
                  <l>But if that you throw her, ſhéel ſhow you a Beare</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my love O, there is none &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her fine daintie Foot is of the fourteens,</l>
                  <l>I love my Love, and ſhe loveth me:</l>
                  <l>And I can tell you that completely it ſeemes,</l>
                  <l>I muſt ſpeak her pr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſes cauſe love is between's,</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my love O, there is none &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If I ſhould marry with one that were proud,</l>
                  <l>I love my Love and ſhe loveth me:</l>
                  <l>Shee would deſire more then can wel be alowd,</l>
                  <l>From ſuch haughty creatures my ſelfe I will ſhrowd,</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my love O, there is none &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And if I ſhould marry with one that is faire,</l>
                  <l>I love my Love, and ſhee loveth me:</l>
                  <l>Perhaps Cornu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing might fall to my ſhare,</l>
                  <l>And ſo ſhe might work me unto much diſpare,</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my love O, there is none doth know</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>how I doe love thee.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And if I ſhould chance to wed one that is ſmall,</l>
                  <l>I love my Love, and ſhee loveth me:</l>
                  <l>Then ſhee is not able to doe ought at all,</l>
                  <l>And yet ſhéel be apt to ſcold and to brall,</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my love O, there is none &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If I ſhould chance for to marry a ſcold,</l>
                  <l>I love my Love, and ſhée loveth me:</l>
                  <l>Then I muſt alwayes by her be controld,</l>
                  <l>And then my libertie would be quite ſold,</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my love O, there is none &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Well, I my choiſe of the firſt meane to kéepe,</l>
                  <l>I love my Love, and ſhée loveth me:</l>
                  <l>For ſhee will be quiet when ſhe is aſleepe,</l>
                  <l>And our affections are ſetled deepe:</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>O my love O, there is none &amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus to conclude, you that heare my Song,</l>
                  <l>I love my Love, and ſhe loveth me:</l>
                  <l>When I am wedded Ile praiſe my wives tong,</l>
                  <l>But then it never ſhall doe me once wrong.</l>
                  <lg type="refrain">
                     <l>
                        <hi>With O my Love ô, there is none doth know</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How I doe love thee.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>M. P.</hi> for <hi>F. Groue,</hi> neere the Sarazens Head with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out New-gate.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
